Finding Aid for Stewart family papers, 1890-1991
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Stewart family papers 1890-1991, 1950-1991
Stewart family
1 oversize folder
3 linear feet
85424 Aa 2 UAm
Papers of R. R. Stewart, United Presbyterian missionary in India and adjunct research investigator of the University of Michigan Herbarium, and papers of his wife, Hladia Porter Stewart, educator at Kinnaird College in Lahore and later Gordon College in Rawalpindi, Pakistan. Reminiscences and other autobiographical writings, correspondence, diary, articles concerning flora of India and Pakistan, and files relating to teaching and missionary work of R. R. Stewart; also letters, memoirs and poetry of Hladia Porter Stewart; and photographs
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Ellen Stewart Daniels (Donor No. 6348 ) in December 1991, February 1992 and March 1992.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open without restriction.
Ralph Randles Stewart, his first wife, Isabelle Darrow Stewart, and his second wife, Hladia Porter Stewart, were teachers and missionaries to that portion of the Indian sub-continent which became Pakistan in 1947. Ralph and Isabelle Stewart were both botany teachers and both functioned as amateur botanists, identifying and collecting examples of the flora from various regions of northern India and Pakistan. Hladia Stewart was an English teacher/missionary who wrote numerous stories, plays, travel articles and poems reflecting the lifestyle of northern India.
Ralph Stewart was born in upstate New York in 1890 and received his undergraduate degree in botany from Columbia University in 1911. Immediately after graduation, he accepted a teaching position in botany at Gordon College in Rawalpindi, northern India near the Afghanistan border.
He returned to Columbia in 1914 and began work on his Ph.D. During this period he married his first wife, Isabelle Caroline Darrow. After receiving his Ph.D in botany from Columbia, he and Isabelle returned to Gordon College in 1917 as botany teachers.
In 1933, Stewart became the principal of Gordon College and remained in that position until 1955 when church policy mandated he relinquish the post. He became vice-principal until his retirement in 1960 when he joined the staff at the University of Michigan as a research assistant helping to identify plant species from northern India and Pakistan.
After the death of Isabelle in 1953, Stewart married Hladia Porter in 1954. They moved to Ann Arbor in 1960 and formally retired to The Westminster Gardens in Durant, California in 1981. Here he became politically active in environmental issues, delivered numerous talks about his teaching career and botanical interests, and wrote for the community newspaper. At this writing (1992), R.R. Stewart is alive and resides in a full care facility in California.
Hladia Stewart was born in India of missionary parents in 1896. Her father ended his career as principal of Gordon College in 1932. Hladia received her BA at Woodstock School in Landown, India and a Master's Degree from The College Of Wooster, Wooster, Ohio in 1919. After graduation, she returned to India to teach English at Kinnaird College, a girls school in Lahore. Following her marriage to Ralph Stewart in 1954, she moved to Gordon College where she was appointed Director of Women in addition to her teaching duties. She died in 1984.
The Stewart Family Collection consists of two linear feet of documents and photos relating to the life of Ralph Randles Stewart and one linear foot relating to the life and writings of Hladia Porter Stewart. Both spent most of their lives on the northern Indian subcontinent.
Subjects:
Botany.; Gordon College (Rawalpindi, Pakistan); India.; Kinnaird College for Women.; Missionaries--India.; Old age.; Pakistan.; Stuart family.; University of Michigan. University Herbarium.; Presbyterian Church--Missions--India.; Stewart, R. R. (Ralph Randles), 1890-; Stewart, H. P. (Hladia Porter)
Contributors:
Stewart, R. R. (Ralph Randles), 1890-; Stewart, H. P. (Hladia Porter)
Genre Terms:
Diaries.
- Ralph Randles Stewart
  The Ralph Stewart portion of the collection is separated into those materials relating to his personal life, his botanical interests and writings, and his teaching career in that area of India which became Pakistan in 1947.
  The personal portion of Ralph Stewart's collection consists primarily of writings and reflections created after his retirement. These writings reflect upon his early life and family in upstate New York and New York City. The period of his life spent while in India is not well documented in these papers. Most of Stewart's reflections were written late in his life and seem designed to be delivered as speeches or expanded upon as journal articles. The collection does include some contemporary material relating to travel in parts of northern India. There are also numerous letters relating to his travel experiences and to the people he met while returning to India late in 1944.
  Stewart was one of the earliest botanists to begin studying the flora of northern India. His writings document the findings of numerous trips away from Lahour. This portion of the collection consists of his published checklists and observations, some with annotations, and his notes. Most of the notes were written after retirement but a small amount of contemporary material is included.
  A short unpublished paper relating to a particular plant collecting trip and written by Isabelle Stewart (Ralph's first wife) is included in a folder at the end of his collection.
  - Biographical/Personal
    - Family history of the Stewart family 1797-1890, circa 1970-1980 (Box 1)
    - General autobiographical writings 1890-1991, circa 1970-1991 (Box 1)
    - Early autobiography 1890-1916, circa 1970-1980 (Box 1)
    - Autobiography, covers 1917-1960 (circa 1970) (Box 1)
    - Autobiography 1960-1980 (Box 1)
    - Autobiography 1981-1991 (Retirement) (Box 1)
    - Diary 1912 (Box 1)
    - Hobbies and interests, covers 1890-1990 ca 1980 (Box 1)
    - Botanical autobiography undated (Box 1)
      reflections on a career in botany
    - Personal documents: birth certificate, diplomas, passports, etc. (Box 1)
    - Reminiscences and reflections 1918-1989, 4 notebooks (in 2 folders) (Box 1)
    - Essays, circa 1981-1990 (Box 1)
    - Articles written for retirement newspaper 1985-1991 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence 1897-1978 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence 1979-1991 (Box 1)
    - "English family names" 1950 (Box 1)
      (a lecture delivered on Pakistani radio)
    - Citations and awards 1914, 1941, 1950-1961, undated (Box 1)
    - Clippings 1911-1980 (Box 1)
  - Botanical Writings
    - Botanical notes 1977-1990 (Box 2)
    - "Bibliography" 1915-1980 (Box 2)
    - "The Flora Of Ladak, Western Tibet," 1917 (Box 2)
      (annotated)
    - "Ferns of Mussoorie and Dehra Dun," 1942 (Box 2)
      (copy of published article with handwritten margin notes)
    - "Grasses Of Northwest India," 1945 (Box 2)
    - "Swat-Chitral Journal," 1953 (Box 2)
      (handwritten notes regarding botanical observations made in two geographic areas of northern India)
    - "Flora of Panjar and Karot Valleys, Kahuta Tehsil, Rawalpindi District," circa 1960-1968 (Box 2)
    - "The Flora of the Kurram Valley," 1967 (Box 2)
    - "Check List of the Grasses of Kashmir," 1967 (Box 2)
    - "Revised Check List of the Pteridophytes of Mussoorie and Dehra Dun," 1970 (Box 2)
    - "Plants of Pakistan," undated (Box 2)
    - "The Flora of Pakistan," 1967-1987 (Box 2)
    - Writings about the flora of Pakistan undated (Box 2)
    - Plants of Westminster Gardens 1981-1991 (Box 2)
  - Teaching and Missionary Work
    - Gordon College
      - Notes and writings about the college undated (written after retirement) (Box 2)
      - Commemorative journal to mark the departure of Ralph and Hladia Stewart 1960 (Box 2)
      - "In the Shadow of the Himalayas," 1942 (a monograph containing a chapter on the history of Gordon College by Ralph Stewart) (Box 2)
    - Notes and writings about the United Presbyterian Church in India undated Travels, 1912-1972 (Box 2)
    - Photographs
      (also oversize folder, UAm)
      - India
        - People 1952-1963 (Box 2)
        - Scenes, no people undated (Box 2)
        - United Presbyterian Mission Group photos 1922-1956 (Box 2)
        - Photo album 1911-1922 (Box 2)
      - Self and family 1836-1969 (Box 2)
- Isabella Darrow Stewart
  - "Among the Himalayas: the plant collector at work," 1940 (Box 2)
    (typed article)
- Hladia Porter Stewart
  The second portion of the collection is made up of the writings of Hladia Porter Stewart. Consisting of numerous unpublished and privately printed books of poetry, plays and stories, these writings all relate to India. During her years in India, she contributed articles to local English language newspapers and magazines. Hladia Stewart was also an artist and some of her written work is illustrated with black and white drawings and watercolors. One small folder contains contemporary information about her teaching experiences at a girls college in India during the 30's and 40's. Another small folder contains material about the violence she observed during the creation of the Pakistani nation in 1947.
  - Personal
    - Hladia Porter Stewart by herself 1896-1954 Autobiographical Sketches (Box 3)
    - "In The Land Of The Five Rivers," undated (Box 3)
      (handwritten drafts of her autobiography dealing with her early life in India)
    - Hladia Porter Stewart by Ralph Stewart 1896-1984 (Box 3)
    - Relief Work 1947 (Box 3)
      (experiences during the creation of the state of Pakistan)
    - Hladia Porter Stewart's wedding 1954 (Box 3)
    - Personal effects: birth and death certificate, marriage license, etc. (Box 3)
    - Correspondence
      - Family 1858, 1861, 1863 (Box 3)
      - Personal 1933-1975 (Box 3)
    - Photographs
      - Family 1897-1976 (Box 3)
  - Writings and Drawings
    - Poetry
      - "Punjab Pictures," 1979 (Box 3)
      - "Kashmir Pictures," 1979 (Box 3)
      - Untitled Work undated (missing first 21 pages) (Box 3)
    - Stories undated (Box 3)
    - Plays undated (Box 3)
    - Poetry undated (Box 3)
    - Children's Stories undated (Box 3)
    - "The Romantic City," undated (Box 3)
      (a manuscript guide book and history of Lahore)
    - "The Romantic City," undated (Box 3)
      (handwritten drafts in 3 notebooks)
    - Water color sketches of plants and animals 1942-1952 (Box 3)
    - "Exhibition of Paintings," 1956 (Box 3)
      (catalog of art exhibit arranged by Department of Fine Art, University of Punjab including works by Hladia Stewart)
    - "Kashmir and Other Places and Stray Thoughts," undated (Box 3)
      (handwritten book of poetry and watercolors)
    - Travel writings 1925, 1950, undated (Box 3)
    - Newspaper articles undated (Box 3)
      (written by Hladia Stewart for "The Civil And Military Gazette" published in Lahore)
    - Magazine Articles 1956, 1958, 1962 (written by Hladia Stewart for "Pakistan Quarterly" published in Karachi) (Box 3)
  - Kinnaird College
    - "The Last Word," 1963 (Box 3)
      (a history of Kinnaird College with a chapter by Hladia Stewart)
    - Personal reflections about teaching at Kinnaird College (Box 3)